TOM WEAVER : The one emblematic movie monster
of the 1950s emerged , in 3-D , no less ,
from Universal Pictures ,
the studio which had already led the field for over two decades .
Science fiction expert Bill Warren calls it
" one of the most famous monsters ever created . "
Another sci-fi authority , Bob Burns , says it 's among the best monsters ever designed ,
and that despite its Johnny-come-lately status ,
it fits right in with Frankenstein , The Wolf Man , The Mummy ,
and all the rest of the great movie monsters of old .
The characters in the movie call him The Gill Man .
The people who made the movie affectionately called him The Beastie .
We call him The Creature from the Black Lagoon .
Out of the Devonian Period , when life crawled out of the sea , it came .
From fishlike thing to mammal , from mammal to a man-like horror of the sea
with the heart of a human , filled with hate , and a man-like instinct to love .
My name is Tom Weaver and together we 'll go back to that black lagoon
and take a peek behind the scenes at one of the best and most famous
monster movies from the second-half of the 20th century .
In the beginning , there was William Alland .
Alland was the man who came up with the idea for Creature from the Black Lagoon
and who produced the picture .
Alland was born in Delmar , Delaware ,
and he began his show business career as an actor with a Baltimore troupe .
A short time later , he moved to New York City ,
arriving there with a few belongings , $ 25 , and the ambition to work on Broadway .
He took acting courses , and he did some acting at the Henry Street Settlement House ,
which is where he met Orson Welles .
This was in the ' 30s .
And Welles was then on the verge of forming his famous
Mercury Players acting company .
Alland started working with the Mercury Players on stage and on the radio ,
where he was part of the cast of the notorious Halloween , 1938 ,
War of the Worlds CBS radio broadcast ,
which was so realistic it caused a panic among listeners ,
and Welles and Alland were nearly thrown into jail .
Alland and Welles continued to associate for years .
Alland also acted in some of Welles ' movies , including Citizen Kane .
Where Alland played the reporter whose face you never see ,
the one who goes through the whole movie in shadow ,
trying to find out what Charles Foster Kane 's dying word , " Rosebud , " meant .
I 'm going to be interrupting myself several times in the next few minutes
while I try to tell you about the genesis of this movie .
So much to say , and only 79 minutes to say it in .
We 're looking here at a shot of Will Rogers Beach in Santa Monica ,
a little west of Universal .
William Alland also socialized with Orson Welles ,
and at some point in the ' 40s , perhaps during the making of Citizen Kane ,
he was invited to have dinner at Welles ' home .
It was a little bit of a party , I guess ,
because Orson Welles ' girlfriend was there , Dolores del Rio ,
who was a Mexican actress , and Alland was there ,
and a guy named Gabriel Figueroa ,
who was a Mexican cinematographer , and eventually quite a famous one .
He photographed The Pearl , he shot a lot of Luis Buñuel 's movies ,
he shot John Ford 's The Fugitive with Dolores del Rio ,
and he got an Academy Award nomination for best cinematography
for The Night of the Iguana , 1964 , for director John Huston .
Huston later gave Figueroa one of his last jobs , maybe the last job .
Figueroa photographed Huston 's Under the Volcano in the 1980s ,
when he , Figueroa , was almost 80 .
On the right is Julio López , who later changed his name to Perry Lopez
and became a busy B-movie star and an A-movie character actor .
He played Jack Nicholson 's former partner , Escobar the cop ,
in Chinatown and The Two Jakes .
So here they all are at this dinner party at Orson Welles ' home .
Just the four of them , I think .
And Gabriel Figueroa somehow gets onto the subject of a real-life , half-man half-fish
that lives in the Amazon River , near a village .
According to Figueroa , once a year it comes out of the Amazon and claims a maiden ,
and then it returns to the Amazon and the village is safe for another year .
Everybody just stared at Figueroa , I guess . He could tell they thought he was kidding .
And he started getting sort of worked up , and he insisted that it was absolutely true
and that the people who live on the Amazon talk about it all the time .
And he said he 'd once seen a photograph of the monster
and that he could get a print of that photograph if they didn 't believe him .
Notice the little rubber pinkie claw , instead of scratching the sand ,
just bends out of shape .
For about five minutes Figueroa kept talking very earnestly about
this half-man half-fish that he said was not a myth , that actually existed .
I have no idea whether he was on the level or not ,
and I don 't know if anybody there ended up believing him ,
but I do know that that little anecdote got lodged in the back of William Alland 's brain .
About 10 years later , Alland landed a job
as a movie producer at Universal International .
He made a lot of Westerns early on ,
he made a Tony Curtis Arabian Nights sort of thing
called The Prince Who Was a Thief .
All moneymakers , I 'm sure , but nothing world-shaking .
Interrupting myself again , here 's a good example
of how movies go together like big jigsaw puzzles .
This is a shot of a speedboat racing across the waters of
Portuguese Bend in California , shot September 30 , 1953 .
Now we 're on the process stage at Universal , a month later , October 29 .
But the image you see in the background on the process screen
was shot at Portuguese Bend on October 5 .
And now we 're 2,500 miles east ,
beneath the surface of Wakulla Springs in Florida , on October 14 .
So this little nothing scene was shot in three different places ,
on four or more different days , two different directors ,
and the three characters in the scene were played ,
or represented , I guess I should say ,
by seven different people . It 's amazing all the work that goes into making a movie .
Anyway , Alland 's there at Universal , making picture after picture ,
and then he starts coming up with ideas for science-fiction movies .
He dreamed up the idea for It Came from Outer Space
and assigned Ray Bradbury to write a treatment .
And right about that same time , maybe as little as just a few weeks later ,
he himself wrote up and submitted to his studio bosses
a story idea called The Sea Monster .
It was just a little three-page thing , where he spent the first page telling the story
of that real-life dinner conversation with Figueroa .
And then he pitched the idea that he should make a movie about that kind of monster .
He wanted the movie to start off with a scene of a dinner conversation ,
just like the one they 'd had in real life with Figueroa ,
and then the movie would go on to show a small expedition
entering an unexplored region of the Amazon ,
accompanied , of course , by a beautiful blonde .
The man-fish spots the blonde and gets a crush on her , and ,
here 's where Alland 's imagination started running away with him a little ,
there was also supposed to be a bad guy on the expedition ,
who wants to catch the creature , and he uses the girl as bait .
Alland 's memo on The Sea Monster ended with the suggestion
that they use one of two endings .
In one ending , the girl is abducted by the creature ,
and her boyfriend has to rescue her and the monster gets killed .
And in the other ending , the creature is captured and brought back to civilization ,
but it escapes and starts terrorizing a little seaport on the South American coast .
Alland wrote , " Needless to say , the monster 's end is brought about
" by his desire for the blonde-haired girl of the expedition . "
Well , you know what that is . That 's King Kong .
Alland took the idea of a man-fish from that conversation with Figueroa
and he got most of the rest of his original story idea from King Kong .
When they made Creature , they did go with the first ending , the simple ending
where the hero rescues the girl and the creature is killed .
But then a few months later , Alland produced a sequel , Revenge of the Creature ,
which used the second ending . The creature is brought back to civilization ,
and it escapes , and it abducts the girl it loves .
In Revenge of the Creature it 's a different girl ,
a different actress from the original Creature .
In Creature , the girl is Julie Adams , but in Revenge , it 's Lori Nelson ,
who , true to Alland 's original story , was a blonde .
I interviewed Alland back around 1995 , two years before he passed away .
At the time when I talked to him ,
I 'd recently watched Creature and Revenge of the Creature back-to-back
and realized , for the first time , that the story was King Kong
set on the water instead of the land .
I asked Alland if he 'd gotten his ideas from King Kong .
And he immediately started laughing . He said he did , absolutely ,
that that was the whole idea , his idea , to redo King Kong , but with a watermonster .
The first writer William Alland assigned to the movie was a fellow named Maurice Zimm ,
who turned in a 59-page draft , titled Black Lagoon , in early December , 1952 .
And it 's sufficiently different from the movie to be worth mentioning here .
In this draft , Dr. Lyman Reed , an undersea explorer ,
risks his life in various underwater adventures in order to raise money
to form an expedition and search the Amazon for the Pisces Man ,
a man-fish that is reported to live there .
We 're looking now , by the way , at footage shot on location
at the Hermosa Beach Aquarium .
Julie Adams and a crew went there during preproduction .
Dr. Reed 's girlfriend , Kay , an heiress , puts up the money herself ,
but insists on going along with the expedition .
Unbeknownst to Kay , her guardian hires an adventurer named Ted Clayton
to find a way to also join the expedition and secretly watch over her .
On the expedition up the Amazon are Dr. Reed , Ted , Kay ,
Kay 's doting companion , Winnie ,
and an explorer named Carl Sloan , who 's got " bad guy " written all over him .
The explorers set traps for the Pisces Man , but it avoids them and weeks go by .
Sloan finally gets fed up , chloroforms Kay and places her on a raft ,
using her as bait for the Pisces Man . The Pisces Man appears .
It has a " huge , fascinating , unbelievable head ,
" with a throat sac like a frog 's and scalloped gills
" that , at a distance , resemble the bobbed hair of a knight of old . "
The Pisces Man kills Sloan and gets away with Kay ,
but Ted follows them to the monster 's grotto and subdues the Pisces Man
by slapping a wrestling hold on it until it passes out .
Kay feels sorry for the Pisces Man , which is locked in a water-filled tank
and brought back to civilization . The tank is taken off the boat and put on a plane .
But Kay sneaks onto the plane when no one else is aboard ,
and unlocks the tank so that the Pisces Man can escape .
The Pisces Man " comes slowly toward her , looms over her ,
" and touches the whiteness of her throat , ever so gently .
" Then , with his eyes still on her , he leaves the plane . "
The military throws out a dragnet , but the Pisces Man is able to elude the searchers .
At one point , it climbs through a window into a house to hide ,
sees a small child sleeping , and adjusts the kid 's blanket before it leaves .
But when the Pisces Man tries to get back into the water by crossing a stretch of beach ,
Dr. Reed shoots him over and over and over .
Reed yells out , " If I can 't have him alive , then I 'll have him dead . "
The Pisces Man crawls into the water , which instantly starts churning
because piranha are attacking it .
Kay dumps Dr. Reed and flies back home with Ted , instead .
The initial Zimm treatment is too much like King Kong , apart from all its other flaws .
But when this early draft was discussed in a December , 1952 , memo ,
the memo writer , who didn 't sign his name , wrote that he was sure it could be developed
into " a very fine horror movie . "
The memo writer , whoever he was ,
also mentions discussing the script with William Alland ,
who said that he would change the ending
" to provide a means of possibly continuing this into sequels
" by keeping the monster alive ,
" or at least leaving his fate in doubt at the end of the picture . "
So as early as 1952 , plans were already being tentatively made
to turn Black Lagoon into a series .
There were a lot of monster 's-eye-view shots in It Came from Outer Space ,
produced by William Alland and directed by Jack Arnold several months earlier .
So Alland and Arnold , again teamed on this picture ,
used that gimmick here , and then again later , in Tarantula .
They also teased the audience by keeping The Gill Man mostly off screen
in its first couple of scenes .
We don 't get to really see the creature until a third of the way through the movie .
For the roar of The Gill Man , which you 'll hear for the first time in a moment ,
the Universal sound technicians reportedly experimented with a lot of strange noises ,
from a foghorn blown underwater , to an opera recording played at low speed .
To be honest , I don 't know what they eventually did use for the roar ,
but I do know that for the Steven Spielberg TV movie Duel ,
a distorted Gill Man roar is used as the sound of the truck crashing .
That 's just great , that big baseball-mitt sized hand
reaching up and grabbing Rodd Redwing by the head .
Everybody I know who saw this movie on its original run in 1954 ,
tells me this was one of the scariest scenes in the movie .
Here 's our first shot of the Rita . Most of the rest of the movie takes place on the Rita .
Back to the script of Black Lagoon . Maurice Zimm handed in his draft ,
and then a writer named Leo Lieberman came in and worked for about two months .
But the story still wasn 't in very good shape . In fact , according to Arthur Ross ,
the Universal front office had turned it down and said they weren 't going to do the picture .
That was the point at which Alland turned to Ross , a Chicago-born screenwriter ,
who did a lot of work whipping the story into shape .
Ross took a look at what had been written and he quickly realized
" that it was an imitation of films that had been made in the genre
" at Universal for 25 years .
" The only difference was that it was an undersea creature
" instead of a mummy , or Frankenstein , or Dracula . "
Ross was , at the time , reading the book The Silent World by Jacques Cousteau ,
and reading that book gave him the idea
that the scientist in the movie should be the hero , not the villain .
Remember , neither of the two scientists in Maurice Zimm 's Black Lagoon was a hero .
One was a publicity-seeking nut , and the other was the movie 's villain ,
a real Snidely Whiplash type .
What Ross wanted to do was make the scientist
" a humanist who enquires of nature rather than dictating to it or exploiting it .
" He 's the one who holds out for not harming the creature . "
Alland understood right away what Ross was trying to do .
According to Ross , Alland knew that the first approach had failed miserably ,
the old-fashioned script that they were trying to work with .
Ross told me ,
" No matter what I 'm doing , whether I 'm writing something just to make a living ,
" or something I really believe is important , I never write down to an audience .
" I don 't believe in that . Audiences are not stupid .
" They may not be geniuses , they may not be specialists in fields ,
" but they are reasonably intelligent people , in the main , and for that reason
" I always felt that I would present what I thought was not only a melodramatic device ,
" but also a study of characters in conflict .
" The conflict , in this case , would be these people versus the creature .
" The more they attack him , the more he attacks them .
" I wrote intelligent people doing intelligent things .
" Everyone , that is , except for the aggressive person , Richard Denning ,
" who wanted the creature dead and mounted ,
" considering that just as good as live and left alone .
" He was unintelligent and he was arrogant , and he caused the difficulties .
" And those difficulties finally had to be rectified in violence ,
" because by that time , the creature was a violent and beset thing
" that had no choice but to fight them . "
After Ross finished up , one last writer , Harry Essex , was brought in .
A few months earlier , Essex had had the very simple job
of turning a 111-page Ray Bradbury treatment
into the screenplay of It Came from Outer Space , which he did ,
and undeservedly got a solo screenplay credit for it .
In subsequent years , Essex was more than happy to try to take all the credit
for It Came from Outer Space ,
and I 'm afraid he liked to try to take all the credit for Black Lagoon , too .
Writers had been working on Black Lagoon for months ,
many drafts of the screenplay had been written ,
and Arthur Ross had gotten it all whipped into shape .
But to hear Essex tell it , when he was hired , all Universal gave him to work with was
" a very , very poorly-written short story .
" Just the basic idea of a fish that had been discovered in the jungle .
" Universal had bought the story for very little money , and assigned me to it .
" And I was bitter and angry .
" I didn 't want to do anything with a title like Creature from the Black Lagoon .
" It was an embarrassment to me . "
I should add , at this point , that the title was just Black Lagoon when Essex worked on it ,
but I 'm sure you 're already taking all these comments of his with a grain of salt .
Essex went on to tell me , " Universal pleaded with me to do the picture .
" And so I began to redevelop the whole damn thing .
" It 's pretty much formula for the kind of horror stories we used to do in those days .
" Except in this particular case , I added the Beauty and the Beast theme .
" The whole idea was to give the creature a kind of humanity .
" All he wants is to love the girl , but everybody 's chasing him .
" It 's an old formula of mine that I 've used with great success . "
( SIGHING ) Harry , Harry , Harry ...
Some interesting touches in the various scripts that never made it to the screen .
For one thing , the original intent was to keep The Gill Man off camera
until at least the middle of the movie .
Universal ended up spending so much money on The Gill Man costume
that , I guess , understandably ,
they finally decided they wanted to show him early and often .
But all you see of him in the first halves of the early scripts are flash shots ,
you see him in silhouette , you see him in shadow , et cetera .
And there was an evocative scene , also not filmed ,
where the captain of the Rita talks about the fable of a beautiful mermaid
who once lived in one of the Amazon 's hidden lagoons .
" It was a very beautiful legend about how this mermaid ,
" she failed in love with a man on a ship . And nobody will believe him .
" And then one day , when the time came for him to go away ,
" she followed him , far out into the Amazon , only to lose her way
" and be devoured by the crocodiles .
" Who knows ? Maybe this mermaid , she was even the wife of this half-man half-fish . "
That dialogue was designed to be heard as narration
over a montage of water and jungle images .
And it would have explained The Gill Man 's fascination with Julie Adams .
Now , I 'm trying to tell the story behind Creature
in some sort of chronological order ,
but here I wanna jump ahead and mention that according to Chris Mueller ,
the makeup department sculptor who sculpted the head and hands of The Gill Man ,
when Universal was getting ready to make the second Creature movie ,
there was some talk of having The Gill Man and a female creature in the sequel .
Needless to say , there is no female creature in the sequel , Revenge of the Creature ,
nor have I seen a draft of the Revenge of the Creature script
that mentions a female creature , and I think I 've seen all of them .
So , I guess it was just an idea being kicked around .
I 'll talk a little more about that later .
( GROANS ) Eight days .
All we dig up are enough stones to pave a road .
WEAVER : All the scenes in and around Dr. Maia 's camp ,
the fossilized arm sticking out of the rock wall ,
the scene of The Gill Man killing the natives in the tent ,
and now these digging scenes , were all shot on the Universal back lot ,
at a spot called Sierra Canyon .
A few months earlier , Jack Arnold was shooting another movie in Sierra Canyon ,
It Came from Outer Space .
Most of the desert exteriors for It Came from Outer Space
were shot on location in the Mojave Desert .
But when Richard Carlson goes down into the meteor crater and finds the spaceship ,
those scenes were shot right here in Sierra Canyon .
They avoided showing the water and all the trees , of course , because in that movie
Carlson was supposedly in a crater in the middle of the Arizona desert .
Over hundreds of years , perhaps over thousands of years ,
the current would break it up .
If there is a dead end ...
WEAVER : Ernest Nims , who was the supervisor
of the editorial department at Universal ,
often made script suggestions .
And one recommendation he made for Creature
was in connection with the early scene
where The Gill Man 's arm reached up out of the Amazon for Julie Adams ' ankle
as she stood on the riverbank .
In a memo , he asked , " Is the creature that we see in the inland water
" the same as the one in the Black Lagoon ? This will be confusing to the audience .
" Why not show the creature following the boat
" when they take the trip up the river to the Black Lagoon ?
" This would not only give added suspense , but would clarify the story point . "
And , you know , that was a good suggestion .
The movie 's famous now , and we know there 's only one Gill Man ,
but in 1954 , when people were seeing it for the first time ,
a Gill Man in Dr. Maia 's camp and another in the Black Lagoon
might have been misleading .
So , sure enough , somebody added a shot to the script .
As the Rita chugs toward the Black Lagoon , there 's a shot of The Gill Man following .
It was a high shot down from the deck of the boat ,
showing The Gill Man just below the surface .
" A long , shark-like shadow , slithering through the water , follows the vessel .
" As he lifts one hand out of the water , we recognize it as the green , taloned thing
" we had seen poking out of the inland water at the geological camp . "
Okay , fine , so the shot 's in the movie , but then , watch this cut right here in a second .
That 's where the shot was before somebody took it out .
You can even hear the music abruptly jump ahead .
They must have taken it out at the last minute , and they didn 't have the time ,
or maybe they just didn 't have the inclination , to fix the music .
They just let it skip ahead very noticeably .
Who took the shot out , and why , I have no idea .
Universal briefly considered shooting Black Lagoon in Eastmancolor .
And of all the Universal sci-fi movies of the ' 50s ,
this is the one that really would have benefited from color , I think .
Creature would have been dynamite in color .
In fact , if the colorization fad hadn 't died out , and if they finally could have gotten it right ,
I would have had no objection , whatsoever , to seeing Creature colorized .
When I told Bill Alland that Creature and Tarantula and some of his other pictures
would have been great in color , he said exactly the same thing ,
that he would love to see Creature colorized , he said it would look fabulous in color .
But I guess the expense of shooting in color worried Universal .
In color and 3D , they projected that Creature would wind up costing them $ 750,000 .
So , pardon the pun , they scaled Creature down ,
made it in black-and-white 3D ,
which they figured would cost them $ 650,000 .
What are you going to shoot at ?
Does it make any difference ?
WEAVER : This is a little embarrassing , maybe ,
to the memory of Jack Arnold ,
and I 'm jumping ahead of myself again , but I 'll point it out anyway .
On the first day of shooting , Tuesday , October 6 , 1953 ,
the very first shot was the upcoming shot of the Rita
squeezing its way through the narrow opening that leads into the Black Lagoon ,
the paradise from which no man has ever returned .
So Jack Arnold lines up his first shot on the first day of the movie , and ...
Why , it 's a blooper .
What 's that telephone pole doing on the left-hand side of the screen ?
It 's impossible .
WEAVER : Much as I 'd like to , there may not be time to talk about all of the actors
in Creature from the Black Lagoon .
I 've got too much information here about other aspects of the production .
But one I have to talk about is Julie Adams .
Other actresses made more sci-fi movies in the ' 50s ,
Mara Corday , Beverly Garland , Faith Domergue , dozens of others .
And Julie Adams just made the one . But by appearing with the creature ,
the most recognizable of ' 50s movie monsters ,
Julie Adams instantly jumped right to the front of the line .
She was born Betty May Adams in Iowa ,
and she knew she wanted to be an actress from the days of grade-school plays .
In California , to pursue her career goal , she took speech lessons to lose her Iowa accent ,
and played most of her early roles in cheap Westerns for a little company called Lippert ,
each of them made in less than a week .
At that point , she was still using her real name , Betty Adams ,
but at Universal she became Julia Adams , and then Julie Adams ,
and she co-starred in almost two dozen movies there in the ' 50s .
A famous sculptor proclaimed that she possessed the most perfect legs in the world ,
so Universal claimed that they insured her legs for $ 500,000 .
That 's an old , old publicity trick that went back to the ' 40s .
Betty Grable 's legs were insured for a million . And it 's even used today .
Just the other day , Jennifer Lopez insured her legs for 400 million .
Anyway , she had these great legs that were never seen in any of the movies she made ,
mostly Westerns and things like that ,
so , Universal gave her the bathing-suit lead in Creature .
And that instantly became her claim to fame , the movie she 's now best remembered for ,
which is a " distinction " that she takes with humor .
More humor sometimes than at other times , perhaps ,
but she 's always been a good sport about it .
She worked a lot in television , including The Jimmy Stewart Show ,
as Jimmy 's Stewart 's wife , and Yancy Derringer ,
and a recurring part on Murder , She Wrote ,
and she 's still working in front of the cameras today ,
most recently in the documentary about Creature
which you 'll find at the end of this movie .
Adams has also made a few other science fiction and horror movies ,
including The Underwater City , with William Lundigan ,
and Psychic Killer with Jim Hutton , which was directed by her former husband ,
actor-director Ray Danton .
She was also in one of Elvis Presley 's movies ,
the haunted-house comedy Tickle Me .
In case you get confused in the scenes
where Richard Carlson and Richard Denning go underwater ,
if you can 't figure out which is which ,
notice that Carlson has two tanks on his back , and Denning just one .
They did that on purpose so people could tell ' em apart underwater .
All the underwater scenes in Black Lagoon were shot in Florida by a second unit
that was working there at the same time that Jack Arnold was shooting at Universal .
Obviously , none of the actors could be there , they were busy at Universal .
So any time the camera is underwater , know that those scenes were shot in Florida
and that none of the people you 're seeing in those shots are the actual actors .
They hired two college students to double for Richard Carlson and Richard Denning .
A girl named Ginger Stanley doubled for Julie Adams ,
and Ricou Browning , who I 'll talk about more later ,
played The Gill Man .
Today it 's easy to overlook what an amazing accomplishment
Creature 's underwater photography was in 1953 .
You have to keep in mind that 3-D was a fairly new process then ,
and there were still a lot of bugs to iron out ,
and now here 's Universal trying to figure out a way to take a 3-D camera underwater .
I think that 's impressive enough , right there , but on top of that ,
it had to be a portable motion-picture underwater camera ,
which was practically unheard of at that time .
This was 1953 , when virtually every other underwater scene in any movie to date
had been photographed by stationary cameras , or through glass tanks .
Universal shot some test footage with this portable underwater camera
and they showed it to people from Life magazine , who were very impressed .
And maybe that 's what gave someone at Universal the idea
that a Life photographer named Peter Stackpole
be asked to take a three-week leave of absence from Life magazine ,
and go to Florida , and photograph the underwater scenes for the movie itself .
Peter Stackpole was one of the four original photographers for Life magazine ,
and he was one of their top photographers ,
taking lots of photos of movie stars when he lived in Hollywood .
He was also very enthusiastic about underwater photography ,
he was an expert swimmer , and he had cameras equipped for underwater filming .
Also in the back of Universal 's mind , of course , was the fact that his participation
would practically ensure a layout on the movie in Life magazine ,
and Universal would also get lots of first-rate stills
of the underwater sequences for their own use .
I don 't know if Stackpole turned them down , or what happened there ,
but the guy Universal ended up hiring to direct the underwater sequences
was a guy named James C. Havens , and that 's a funny story that I 'll save for later .
The underwater scenes of Creature were shot at Wakulla Springs , Florida .
Movies had been shot underwater there in the past .
Some of the Tarzan pictures ,
like Tarzan 's Secret Treasure from the old Johnny Weissmuller days .
And the place was managed by a fellow named Newton Perry .
Our first look at Ricou Browning as the underwater creature .
Newton Perry was also involved with various Florida water shows and things like that ,
and he was obviously known in Hollywood ,
because when Universal decided to shoot part of Creature there ,
he was the man they called .
They asked Perry if he knew of any swimmers that he could recommend ,
and they also asked if he knew of any locations
where they might be able to find something that looked like the Black Lagoon .
Perry said sure , he 'd show ' em around .
But when the time came , he was off in Miami doing something ,
and all of a sudden he wasn 't available .
So Perry called his friend , Ricou Browning , in Tallahassee ,
and asked Ricou to pick the Universal people up at the airport
and take them down to the spring and show it to them .
Ricou was 23 years old at the time , and attending Florida State .
He 'd worked for Newton Perry in the past ,
producing water shows at Weeki Wachee Springs .
Ricou went to the airport and picked up Jack Arnold
and a man named Scotty Welbourne ,
who was going to be photographing the underwater scenes in Creature .
Together , they went out to the spring , and Arnold and Welbourne liked it .
Wakulla Springs is in the middle of nowhere .
And in 1953 , and even right now , if you go there ,
it would be like going to Florida with Ponce de León when he landed .
It 's been that well protected .
The bowl of the spring is about five-acres big .
It 's the largest spring in the state of Florida , and it has the largest water flow .
By the way , Ricou Browning was also a cave diver ,
which means that he was hired at times to go down into underwater caves
to map them out .
The bottom of Wakulla Springs slopes down inside a cave , and it just keeps going .
Ricou doesn 't know if anybody 's ever gone the distance
as to how far you could actually go .
The deepest that Ricou and the cave divers he used to work with
ever went with air hoses there was , he says , 100 , at the most 110 , 120 feet .
But , of course , they didn 't have some of the equipment , or the helium mixes
that divers have nowadays ,
so naturally they couldn 't go as deeply as divers today .
Much more recently , divers equipped with this new gear and the new mixed gases
have gone 200-300 feet down into Wakulla Springs .
But , as Ricou said , " They still may not have found the bottom . "
Anyway , Scotty Welbourne had a movie camera with him that day at Wakulla Springs ,
and he said to Ricou , " Would you do me a favor ?
" Would you swim in front of the camera so we can get some perspective
" of the size of the logs , or the fish , or whatever with a human body ? "
Ricou said , " Sure , " and he did swim for Welbourne .
Arnold and Welbourne were very happy with the spring .
And Ricou took ' em to the airport and they left .
And , two or three weeks later , Ricou got a call from Jack Arnold , who said ,
" We looked at the footage , we love the spring , and we love the way you swim .
" I like your style . How would you like to be the Creature of the Black Lagoon ? "
And Ricou said , " Fine . Let 's have at it . "
Arnold said they 'd send him tickets so he could come out to Universal ,
and they 'd build an outfit for him to wear . And the rest , as they say , is history .
Come on , David . You can play house later .
WEAVER : The script has Richard Denning say something obnoxious in every scene ,
so that we never forget that he 's gonna be the heavy .
Browning went out to California and reported to Universal ,
where various outfits for The Gill Man were being devised .
I should interrupt myself here and mention that William Alland 's concept of The Gill Man
was much more human than The Gill Man we see in the movie .
Alland had a sculptor sculpt the head of a very sad , beautiful monster .
In fact , he told me , " It wasn 't a monster . It was far more attractive ,
" more romantic-looking than the beast they ended up with .
" It had fish lips and gills and a vaguely fishlike face ,
" sort of an aquatic development of a man . "
Alland told me , " It would still frighten you ,
" but it would frighten you because of how human it was , not the other way around . "
And the studio said , " Get outta here , that 's not scary enough . "
That 's when the Universal makeup department took over .
Kay doesn 't know there 's a creature in the Amazon ,
but she does know from Lucas that it 's full of nine-foot killer catfish .
You couldn 't get me in that lagoon with dynamite .
Here comes the best and the most famous scene in the movie ,
as Julie Adams takes a dip in the lagoon
and is ogled from below by yet another male admirer ,
The Gill Man .
Julie Adams is doubled in this scene by Ginger Stanley ,
a " mermaid " swimmer at Weeki Wachee Spring .
When the camera is underwater , it 's Florida cinematographer Scotty Welbourne 's camera ,
and you 're looking at Ginger Stanley .
When the camera is above water , then it 's cinematographer William Snyder
photographing Julie Adams in Park Lake at Universal .
Ricou Browning 's swimming performance in this scene
is the poetic / dramatic highlight of the movie .
The thing that makes the creature as image and myth
are the wonderful , dynamic , swimming Ricou shots you 're about to see .
There 'll be no dialogue for the next few minutes , so now might be a good time
to talk a little about the music of Creature from the Black Lagoon .
Sci-fi movie music expert David Schecter ,
who releases classic SF film scores on CD
under the umbrella title Monstrous Movie Music , calls the Creature score
" one of the most varied and memorable in all of ' 50s sci-fi horrordom . "
" Part of the experience of watching a creature film
" is the considerable musical accompaniment . "
And he 's right . A hefty 63 % of Creature has background music .
Of the 44 cues listed on Creature 's cue sheets ,
29 were composed specifically for the movie ,
with the other 15 lifted from prior Universal pictures .
The 29 originals were , according to Schecter ,
composed by Hans J. Salter , 12 , Henry Mancini , 10 ,
and Herman Stein , seven . The music we 're hearing right now is by Herman Stein ,
and the cue is called Kay and the Monster .
" The older films that contributed library music to Creature 's score
" were from many different genres , "
writes Schecter . " Some , like Mr. Peabody and the Mermaid ,
" were water-themed pictures ,
" which is why the music was considered for use in Creature from the Black Lagoon .
" And also why it was so well-suited .
" Westerns also played a role in Creature 's score ,
" as they did in other Universal sci-fi scores of the ' 50s .
" But what sets Creature 's score apart from that of many other Universal sci-fi films
" is its reliance upon a single musical motif ,
" Herman Stein 's memorable three-note creature theme .
( TRUMPETS PLAYING THREE-NOTE THEME )
WEAVER : " In the film , practically every time you see the creature ,
" or his hands , or his back , or his feet ,
" or even his wet footprints , you hear his three-note theme ,
" often played on flutter-tongued trumpets . "
Schecter calls the three-note Creature theme , " a memorable musical signature , "
which it certainly is .
It 's instantly recognizable , even when it crops up in non-Universal sci-fi movies ,
like Women of the Prehistoric Planet and Dracula vs. Frankenstein
that lifted music from Creature .
People who write about this movie often speculate
that this scene here was an inspiration to Steven Spielberg
when he shot some of the scenes of Jaws .
Because the plot of Creature is so indebted to King Kong , I think back to Kong .
This scene of a curious Gill Man playfully poking and touching her legs
makes me think of the scene in Kong ,
where King Kong takes Fay Wray up to the mountain top ,
and pokes her and tickles her .
I also wanna talk briefly about some of the people who worked on the Creature costume .
Prominent among them was a creative designer named Milicent Patrick .
Talk about Beauty and the Beast . She was born an Italian baroness ,
she was a former Goldwyn Girl , a model , an interior decorator , an artist .
She was the first woman animator for Walt Disney Studios ,
and she helped design the creature and did some of the final painting on the costume .
Chris Mueller was one of the sculptors ,
Tom Case was a painter on the various Gill Man suits ,
and Jack Kevan , who was Bud Westmore 's right-hand man ...
He was Bud Westmore 's right and left-hand man .
Jack Kevan did a little of everything .
Kevan worked as Westmore 's assistant , but he was a hell of a lot more than that .
He was a real hands-on guy who did most of whatever work had to be done .
He was born in Pittsburgh , attended UCLA ,
and he went to work doing makeup at MGM in 1932 .
He made up the main characters in The Wizard of Oz , and then , during World War ll ,
he made prosthetic appliances for badly wounded men throughout the Pacific .
After the war , he got a job at Universal ,
where he worked on A and C Meet Frankenstein , It Came from Outer Space ,
Man of a Thousand Faces , Tarantula , scores of movies .
And in 1958 he and Creature 's dialogue director , Irvin Berwick ,
struck out on their own and made a low-budget horror film
called The Monster of Piedras Blancas ,
a thinly-disguised attempt to duplicate the success of Creature
with a lookalike sea monster .
Jack Kevan told me ,
" They were lucky in finding a person like Ricou Browning ,
" a person who could swim underwater ,
" and not be restricted by all the equipment he had to wear .
" We took a full body cast of him . On top of his figure , we built the monster to fit him ,
" mold wise , in several pieces . I can 't tell you how many now ,
" but I would guess between six and ten . They were cast in foam rubber ,
" which at the time was something new . The costume fit him pretty skintight . "
It sure did . Ben Chapman , the 6 ' 5 " actor who played the creature at Universal ,
describes The Gill Man suit as fitting as closely as an outer layer of skin .
Luckily , neither Ricou nor Ben was claustrophobic .
Because anybody who gets into a suit like that and finds out they are claustrophobic
is in a world of trouble .
Once you were in that suit ,
your eyeballs and the inside of your mouth was all that was showing .
Unfortunately , nothing is left of any of The Gill Man costumes today .
They were made of foam rubber , and that stuff doesn 't last .
Even the molds used to make the suits have been destroyed .
Universal threw them away years ago to make some room .
It 's a small thing , but I was always bothered by the fact that they want us to believe
the creature was able to crack the boom just by his powerful swimming .
For one thing , the boat 's not even anchored ,
the creature would just tow the boat around the lagoon .
Frank Lovejoy was originally considered for the starring role in Creature .
Lovejoy was the police lieutenant hero of Warner Bros. ' House of Wax ,
a huge 3D hit earlier that year ,
and maybe that was part of the reason Universal thought of him for Creature .
But then they decided to go with Richard Carlson instead .
For the part of Dr. Maia , Universal first thought of Ramon Novarro .
Ramon Novarro was a Mexican-born leading man
who became a big , Rudolph-Valentino-like star in the silent era .
He had the title role in one of the greatest silent epics , MGM 's Ben Hur .
But instead of Novarro , Universal went with Antonio Moreno ,
who back in silent days was kind of like the poor man 's Ramon Novarro .
Creature was one of Moreno 's final screen roles . He died rich in 1967 .
This was strange at a movie company famous for its monsters ,
but Universal tried to avoid putting an exploitative title on the movie .
They called it , simply , Black Lagoon for a long stretch of time ,
but then they decided that that just wasn 't going to cut it
and they sent out a memo requesting submission of alternate titles .
The memo read in part , " The request is for a title that may better suggest
" the shock and mystery value , and perhaps the prehistoric implications of the story .
" However , we have been asked to stay away from words like ' monster ' or ' beast
" to avoid a title that might downgrade the picture . "
Somebody suggested The Web and the Claw ,
and William Alland , who had a lot of success with It Came from Outer Space ,
recommended It Came From Out of the Sea .
The other four titles he suggested were The Demon of the Deep , The Sea Demon ,
The River of Terror , and It Walks the Sea .
Incidentally , when Alland heard in the 1980s
that Universal was thinking of remaking Creature ,
he felt that the studio should do another sequel instead of a remake .
Since the creature that Alland had originally envisioned was so romantic ,
he thought it should have a family , a mate and one or two little ones .
In Alland 's story they were all removed from the Black Lagoon and transported to a lake
on the estate of a very wealthy family in the US .
They can communicate with the family and a whole relationship develops ,
but unfortunately some heavies find out about them
and capture one or both of the children ,
and the mother and father have to go out after them .
Alland wrote it all up and tried to make himself send it in to Universal
during all the many years that the studio talked about doing a new Creature movie ,
but he never could bring himself to submit it .
William Alland passed away in 1997 .
A second unit director named James C. Havens
was hired to direct the underwater second unit stuff in Creature .
And I 'm sure Universal felt very fortunate to have gotten him
and no doubt had a lot of confidence in him .
He 'd been around the movie business most of his life ,
and he 'd been around boats and water practically all his life .
I tried to track him down several years ago and I finally found his phone number ,
but when I called , his wife answered and told me he had died several years before .
But I had a nice conversation with her , because she had married him in 1924 .
And they 'd been married for 65-and-a-half years ,
so I figured she might know a little something about him .
And she made him sound like a real interesting guy .
He started out as an art director at MGM around 1924 ,
the same year he got married , and gradually , he got into marine directing ,
which means he directed the seagoing scenes for movies , big movies .
Like Mutiny on the Bounty with Clark Gable ,
and Captains Courageous with Spencer Tracy , and pictures like that .
And Havens always owned a boat . He had a sailboat first , without any engine ,
and then he and his wife had ketches and motorboats and all kinds of boats .
Then he was a captain in the Marines during World War II ,
a demolition expert for the Marines .
And when John Ford made the movie Mogambo in East Africa ,
Havens shot the animal scenes for Mogambo in Tanganyika .
And he went around scouting locations in a Land Rover
right during the big Mau Mau Rebellion .
She made him sound like a real man 's man ,
a guy who could handle anything that could possibly come up ,
which I 'm sure he was .
So it was so funny , to me anyway ,
to hear what happened to him during Creature from the Black Lagoon .
Havens goes to Florida to direct the underwater scenes
and Scotty Welbourne is there to photograph ' em .
And a few days pass , and William Alland gets a phone call from Florida
from the production manager ,
who tells him , " You 'd better come down here , there 's all hell breaking loose .
" Havens and Welbourne , they 're not getting along . "
Anyway , Alland hears that all hell is breaking loose , so he goes to Florida .
And what 's happening is Havens is afraid to go underwater .
Hang on for a second .
This is sort of an odd shot here , this very blurry shot of a hand ,
followed a few seconds later by a shot of The Gill Man
swimming away in another hard-to-see shot .
Seems to me like shots like these
should have preceded our first good look at The Gill Man .
They 'd have made great teaser shots .
Anyway , I asked Mrs. Havens if her husband liked to dive , and she said , " No , no .
" He didn 't like going under the water at all . " So , in Florida , during the making of Creature ,
the best Havens could do was float on the surface of the water
with a face mask and a snorkel ,
and look down 50 feet or 60 feet or whatever , and try to figure out what was going on .
He had sketched out the way he wanted each shot to be shot ,
but Scotty Welbourne said he couldn 't work that way .
Havens , floating on the surface of the water , couldn 't see what was at the bottom ,
and I guess he was sketching things that weren 't even down there ,
and Welbourne was saying that all he , Welbourne , could do
was take advantage of what was down there at the bottom .
So Bill Alland 's idea was , he 'd put on scuba gear and he 'd go down ,
and maybe that would kind of shame Havens into doing it .
So Alland put on the equipment and he dove down 50 feet ,
where they had underwater light platforms and all kinds of stuff set up ,
and he watched Scotty Welbourne doing his thing down there .
Then Alland came back up and he told Havens ,
" Look , either you go down there , and see what he 's doing and work with him ,
" or you 've just got to get out of the way . "
And Havens said , " Okay , fine , " he 'd just get out of the way .
So , according to William Alland , even though in the opening credits , it says ,
" Underwater sequences directed by James C. Havens , "
Alland says , " He did not have a damn thing to do
" with any of the stuff that went on underwater .
" Scotty Welbourne directed the underwater stuff . "
Ricou Browning also remembers the situation with Havens ,
but doesn 't tell the story the same way Alland did .
Ricou said it wasn 't that Havens was afraid to go underwater ,
it 's just that he wasn 't capable ,
in other words , he wasn 't trained to go underwater .
According to Ricou , " Havens got in an inner tube and put on a face mask
" and he would watch , as much as he could , what was going on .
" He depended a great deal on Scotty Welbourne ,
" and Scotty was a pretty sharp character .
" And Havens just kind of left it to him and us to do our thing .
" He would watch , and comment now and then . "
I asked Ricou , I said , " In a perfect world , should the credits of Creature say ,
" ' Underwater scenes directed by James Havens , '
" or ' Underwater scenes directed by Scotty Welbourne ? " '
And he answered , " I would just say a combination of people .
" I would give Havens credit . "
And the guy who filmed the out-of-water scenes in Creature ,
he was no slouch either . He was a guy named William Snyder ,
who 'd been around for years , and had photographed a lot of pictures
and had received three Oscar nominations in the 1940s .
Aloma of the South Seas ,
The Loves of Carmen and Jolson Sings Again .
After Creature , he worked a lot at Walt Disney Studios .
He also shot The Conqueror , the John Wayne Genghis Khan movie ,
a movie that 's notorious , A , for not being very good ,
and , B , for having been shot on location in Utah near an atomic test site .
A frighteningly high percentage of the cast and crew were later stricken by cancer .
Welbourne 's no longer with us , and maybe that had something to do with it .
But he 'd be 100-and-something years old today ,
and maybe that had something to do with it , too .
... it 's the greatest find yet .
Nothing compares to it .
I 've got the proof here in my lens .
WEAVER : Richard Carlson developing the photograph here
makes me think back to the Gabriel Figueroa story ,
Figueroa saying that he had once seen a photo of the real-life Amazon monster ,
and that he could get a print of that photograph
if Orson Welles and his friends didn 't believe him .
Ben Chapman will be making another appearance
as the creature in a minute or so .
Ben Chapman is a Tahitian , born in Oakland , California ,
while his parents were on a trip to the United States .
He was raised in Tahiti , relocated to the US in 1940 ,
and went to school in the Bay Area of San Francisco .
He worked as a Tahitian dancer in nightclubs before he landed his first movie job ,
a bit in an MGM musical with a Tahitian setting called Pagan Love Song .
He was a dancer in it , but he got along so well with the director
that he also got an additional little part as Rita Moreno 's boyfriend .
He had other small parts like that
before the Korean War sidetracked his movie career .
He served in Korea , and upon his return , he was hired as a stock player at Universal .
Creature was the best movie role he ever had ,
even if all you ever see of him is the inside of his mouth ,
but he kept plugging away for years ,
acting on TV and Jungle Jim movies , and things like that .
Eventually , he moved to Hawaii and got a job with a realty company ,
but his business card had artwork of the creature on it .
For a merman , he takes a fine picture .
This wasn 't imagination , Doctor .
I 'm sorry , David .
What proof do we have if we never find it again ?
WEAVER : Chapman plays The Gill Man in the scenes shot at Universal .
And he says that Jack Arnold insisted he walk like this .
The creature glides in water ,
so Arnold wanted him to glide on land , too , to shuffle like that .
In fact , they sometimes put some lead , maybe as much as 10 pounds of it ,
in the bottoms of his creature boots ,
a reminder for Chapman not to lift his feet when he walked .
I once had a very strange conversation with Henry Escalante ,
the actor who just got attacked .
I located him and called him up , fishing , as it were , for more Creature stories ,
and very , very casually , he told me that he played the creature .
He talked about how hot the suit was and how tough it was to breathe sometimes .
He told me he had a guy with a fan fanning him all the time .
He talked about how much he sweated in the costume
and how much the perspiration burned when it got into his eyes .
He talked about how he got along with Jack Arnold .
He could not have sounded more casual .
He sounded absolutely believable ,
except there wasn 't one word of truth in anything he said .
It was probably the strangest conversation I ever had with anybody about a movie .
DR. MAIA : Quickly !
WEAVER : By the way , you 'll notice that these footprints they 're about to show
don 't match the way the creature was walking .
He dragged his feet , he didn 't take those kinds of steps .
Vision was a problem for both Ben Chapman and Ricou Browning .
For Chapman , they made different sets of eyes for different situations .
It all depended on how far away from the camera he was .
For close-ups of the creature , they gave him eyes that were complete ,
that filled up the whole eye socket , and he could hardly see through those .
Somebody would have to use a flashlight
and point it in the direction they wanted him to walk ,
and Chapman , who could just barely see the light , would head off that way .
For medium shots , the holes in the eyes were a little bigger
and he could see a little better ,
and for long shots , they just gave him eyes with good-size holes in them ,
and he could see just fine .
For Ricou Browning , working underwater , it was a lot harder .
At first , he tried to wear little goggles under the creature mask ,
but once water got in the goggles , you couldn 't get it out .
They thought about giving him a facemask ,
but that made The Gill Man face bulge out too far .
Finally , they just gave up , and he used his naked eyes .
But that was tough , because I guess
the creature mask was just a little bigger than his head ,
and sometimes the eyeholes were a couple of inches from his real eyes .
So seeing out the eyeholes
was kind of like trying to look through a keyhole from a couple inches away .
He said his vision was often very blurred , and that a lot of it was kind of hit and miss .
By the way , the creature suit we see in the movie
was not the first creature suit that the makeup department came up with .
The first one they devised was very different from the eventual design ,
and it was rejected pretty quickly . Ricou Browning described it
as more streamlined than the creature suit we know today .
According to Ricou , " It had less scales , less fins ,
" and the head was more like you were wearing a tight stocking over your face .
" A little bit more human in appearance . "
That early , rejected head was sculpted by Chris Mueller ,
almost certainly from a design by Milicent Patrick .
And as I mentioned earlier ,
when Universal started thinking about making a second Creature movie ,
there was talk of adding a Gill Woman .
The rejected Gill Man head , or something very much like it ,
would have been used as the head of the female creature .
When the rejected head was originally made , it was supposed to be a Gill Man ,
but the eventual Gill Man head used in the picture looked so ferocious
that this more human head ended up looked almost feminine by comparison .
Q Magazine : " This horrendous pseudo-science-fiction melodrama
" revolves , rather wildly , in three dimensions and with considerable excitement ,
" around a poor ancestral fish that never quite made the grade to man .
" However , it ain 't funny , McGee . On the contrary , it 's pretty scary .
" And Creature from the Black Lagoon is a first-rate thriller-chiller of its sci-fi type . "
But when the movie used to play on New York TV ,
the New York Times always called it " about as charming as a dead cat . "
Believe it or not , there is such a thing as rotenone ,
they didn 't make it up for this movie .
It 's a crystalline substance used in insecticides .
Universal decided not to use real rotenone in these scenes ,
so they had to do some experimenting during preproduction .
They combined pure cream with aluminum
for shots of rotenone on the surface of the water ,
and they used pure cream alone for the underwater shots .
Here in one little rowboat are the two leading sci-fi stars of the ' 50s .
Richard Carlson was in It Came from Outer Space ,
The Magnetic Monster , The Maze and Riders to the Stars .
And Richard Denning was in Target Earth , Creature with the Atom Brain ,
The Day the World Ended , and Black Scorpion .
And they were both in Black Lagoon , of course .
So they 're even-steven , sci-fi-wise .
When I talked to Denning and asked about Carlson ,
he wasn 't crazy about the guy .
Denning said Carlson could be uppity ,
and that goes right along with what some other people have told me , too .
The one who said it best was an actor named Michael Fox ,
who worked with Carlson in Magnetic Monster
and Riders to the Stars , and probably half a dozen other movies .
He said Carlson envisioned himself an actor , writer , producer , director .
And Carlson was all those things at various times , by the way .
Fox said it was sad . Carlson was a good-looking guy , he was bright ,
he was quite well read in many areas , but the moment Carlson thought
that somebody else was in authority , he would tell that person how to do his job .
According to Fox , " Carlson was used to being the intellectual limelight on a set .
" He did not like to share it with someone who was , in his opinion ,
" lesser than he . "
And incidentally , Richard Denning , who 's out to bag the creature in this movie ,
certainly did know his way around boats and nets and traps .
When Denning got back from serving in the military during World War II ,
he , like a lot of other young movie actors who 'd had their careers interrupted ,
had a hell of a hard time getting it started again .
He and his actress wife , Evelyn Ankers , had used up all their savings ,
so what they did was move into a house trailer at Paradise Cove ,
and he set up 100 lobster traps . Denning had always loved the water
and boats and everything , so I guess this was almost second nature to him .
He had a rowboat , he couldn 't afford an outboard ,
and he would row the traps out ,
set them in the evenings , and then go out and collect them at daybreak .
The Dennings lived on lobster and sold lobster ,
and years later , when he and Ankers looked back at that time ,
they realized that those were their happiest times .
But then Denning started getting work again .
He played Lucille Ball 's husband on the radio show
that was later changed for TV into I Love Lucy ,
and he started starring in B-movies again and he let the lobster business go .
He died in 1998 , and Richard Carlson died in 1977 .
The Rita was a real boat out on Park Lake on the Universal back lot ,
but some scenes on the Rita were shot indoors on a duplicate Rita ,
on Universal 's process stage .
The scenes at the beginning , for example , of Richard Denning firing the spear gun ,
those were shot indoors
with the jungle projected on a rear projection screen behind them .
And this eerie nocturnal scene here was shot on the process stage ,
at about 9 : 00 in the morning .
The scenes in the creature 's cavernous grotto
were also shot on a set on the process stage .
Here 's Ben Chapman , about to climb onto the boat .
Or , I should say , to try to climb onto the boat .
Once The Gill Man suit got waterlogged , it weighed a ton ,
and even someone as young and strong as Chapman couldn 't climb a rope
with those slippery , wet gloves on and his suit weighing him down .
So what they did was get a big stepladder and put it in the water ,
the top step just below the surface .
And Chapman 's walking up the ladder as he pretends to be climbing the rope .
But the mistake they made was , when he gets scared by the lantern
and lets go of the rope , for a split second ,
you can tell that he 's standing on something in the water .
When Chapman let go of the rope ,
he should 've just dropped straight down into the water like a rock ,
but instead , he stood on the surface of the water for a split second
and then fell off to the side .
Creature from the Black Lagoon was Jack Arnold 's fourth feature film
and his third in 3-D .
He 'd already directed It Came from Outer Space
and a murder drama called The Glass Web with Edward G. Robinson .
Jack Arnold was born on a kitchen table in New Haven , Connecticut ,
the son of young Russian immigrants .
He was raised in New York and began acting on Broadway in the 1930s .
During the war , he worked as a cameraman
for documentary filmmaker Robert Flaherty 's unit .
After his discharge , he made educational and promotional films
with titles like Chicken of Tomorrow for the Agriculture Department ,
while at the same time , continuing to act on stage .
In 1950 , he directed a public-relations film
for the International Ladies ' Garment Workers ' Union , With These Hands .
The film starred Broadway actors
Sam Levene , Arlene Francis and Joseph Wiseman .
With These Hands went into general theatrical release , became a critical success ,
and received an Academy Award nomination as best documentary feature .
Off of that project , he was discovered by Universal ,
who placed him under contract in 1952 .
In addition to the movies he directed , he also produced and directed for TV ,
including such series as It Takes a Thief and Gilligan 's Island .
He was one of the first major sci-fi directors , and as a result ,
his work was , in later years , honored at film festivals ,
in Mill Valley , California , France , Spain and Brazil .
In 1982 , Creature from the Black Lagoon was going to be remade
in color and 3D , a big budget , and with Jack Arnold at the helm .
John Landis was the one who brought the project to Arnold .
Landis was going to executive produce ,
Rick Baker was chosen to furnish the creature ,
based on the same classic design and makeup effects ,
and Nigel Kneale wrote the screenplay , but this new Creature was never made .
Universal decided to put their money behind Jaws 3-D instead .
Jack Arnold died in 1992 .
I never quite understood how they managed to dive
down , down , down , down , to the creature 's lair
and wind up in a cave that 's at sea level , with a beach entrance .
You 'd also think it would be as dark as the ace of spades in there .
This hand-on-the-shoulder gimmick is such a cliché today ,
but it still worked in 1954 . It got a great reaction .
Ernest Nims remembered a scene in It Came from Outer Space
where Barbara Rush did the same thing to Carlson ,
came up from behind and touched him .
It worked there , so Nims suggested they do it again in Creature .
And again it got a scream .
People who saw Creature at a preview
mentioned it on their preview comment cards .
Well , when something worked , Universal never let go .
They used it again in Tarantula , with John Agar on the receiving end ,
The Deadly Mantis with Craig Stevens , Cult of the Cobra with David Janssen ,
Monster on the Campus with Joanna Moore ,
right down the line for the rest of the decade .
One of the creature 's favorite habits
was to pick guys up over his head and throw them .
He did it to the college student on the beach in Revenge of the Creature ,
and he did it to Jeff Morrow at the end of Creature Walks Among Us .
And the plan here was for the creature to pick Zee up and throw him .
According to the script , Zee was going to be thrown into the camera for the 3-D effect .
The actor , Bernie Gozier , was on a wire ,
and he was going to be pulled up into the air that way ,
once Ben Chapman grabbed him and pretended to lift him .
Well , they tried it twice and twice the wire broke .
And finally , Jack Arnold decided to forget it ,
have the creature just grab and choke the guy instead .
But if you watch close enough , you can see in this shot coming up here
that the creature does reach down for the guy 's leg .
They shot that before they found out the wire gag wasn 't going to work .
Julie Adams says Creature was a very pleasant movie
and that they all laughed a lot .
And she particularly liked this scene here .
" We were down on the beach on the edge of the water one day
" doing the scene where the creature has killed one of the natives .
" We were looking down at the body
" and there was this moment where we were all very still .
" Richard Carlson was in his bathing trunks and he had his facemask on his forehead ,
" and in just the way people take off their hats for the dead ,
" he reached up and he took off his facemask .
" He doffed it so seriously that we all started to laugh ,
" and it took a long time to come back together again . It was just too absurd .
" And then we had this wonderful guy who did the clapboard for the different shots ,
" an old vaudevillian .
" The day Whit Bissell 's face was all bloodied up by the creature ,
" this fellow clapped the board , and then he said to Whit ... "
Julie said this out of the corner of her mouth ,
" How are you fixed for blades ? "
Jack Arnold had the same attitude about The Gill Man
that screenwriter Arthur Ross did .
Arnold said in interviews that he set out to make it a very sympathetic character .
In one interview , Arnold said the creature was violent
" because he 's provoked into violence . Inherent in the character
" is the statement that all of us have violence within ,
" and if provoked , are capable of any bizarre retaliation .
" If left alone and understood ,
" that 's when we overcome the primeval urges that we are all cursed with .
" Man 's inhumanity to man
" means not only man 's inhumanity to his own kind ,
" but to anything else , especially something that 's very different from himself .
" You can trace the roots down to primitive tribes , one against the other ,
" in the cities , to this block against the next block , or the Jew against the Arab ,
" the Protestant against the Catholic , the black against the white .
" We have not progressed as human beings
" to differentiate between what is superficial and what is not .
" Of course , the sooner we learn the lesson , the better off we 'll be .
" And that 's what I tried to point out in my science fiction films ,
" in a manner in which an audience would accept it .
" I don 't think they would accept a polemic . They 'd walk out on it ,
" or it 'd be under investigation by the House Un-American Activities Committee ,
" or some such animal .
" My objective was primarily to entertain , but I also wanted to say something .
" If 10 % of the audience grasped it , then I was very successful . "
Whit Bissell , who 's in a number of Jack Arnold movies ,
was a versatile character actor ,
and an ideal choice for the part of the gentle Dr. Thompson .
But he was just as ideally suited for his ruthless mad-scientist roles
in movies like I Was a Teenage Werewolf and I Was a Teenage Frankenstein .
He was one of the most recognizable of 1950s supporting players .
He 's also in sci-fi pictures like Lost Continent ,
Target Earth with Richard Denning ,
Invasion of the Body Snatchers , Jack Arnold 's Monster on the Campus ,
The Time Machine , The Manchurian Candidate , Soylent Green ,
and Psychic Killer with Julie Adams .
Bissell was a native of New York City . He worked on the stage from boyhood ,
and appeared in a number of Broadway plays before he went Hollywood in the mid-1940s .
He worked in movies at first under the name Whitner Bissell ,
and he was in pictures like Holy Matrimony , Destination Tokyo and Brute Force .
His busiest decade for film work was the ' 50s .
He made more than 50 movies in 10 years .
A lot of small parts , but a few co-starring roles , too .
He was also in lots of sci-fi TV series ,
and he was a regular on Irwin Allen 's Land of the Giants .
Whit Bissell died in 1996 .
( DOOR CLATTERING )
It 's a little hard to believe that Bissell , or anybody else ,
could fall asleep guarding a seven-foot-tall killer from the dawn of time .
Maybe it 's that soothing music ,
a Henry Mancini composition called Monster Caught .
It 's funny to think of Henry Mancini
writing music for these Universal monster movies ,
and without credit at that , but this obviously was years before Peter Gunn
and his several Academy Awards
for Breakfast At Tiffany 's and Moon River and Days of Wine and Roses .
He also won over 20 GRAMMYs . And in 1990 , David Schecter tells me ,
Mancini put out a CD called Mancini in Surround ,
and on it , he included some music he wrote for Creature ,
an excellent piece called Monster Gets Mark .
You 'll hear it later during the scene where the creature fights and kills Richard Denning .
Mancini re-orchestrated and slightly recomposed the cues ,
and he conducted them at a much more leisurely pace ,
but it was still clearly Creature music .
Mancini also contributed to the scores of It Came from Outer Space
and Tarantula , and lots of other golden oldies .
KAY : If it weren 't for Mark Williams , I wouldn 't have my work or even a job .
DR. THOMPSON : It 's true , he helped you through your training and gave you a job .
But he needed you just as much as you needed him .
You 're oversimplifying .
You 've more than repaid him many times over .
Why , a good part of his present position at the institute
is due to your valuable research .
And another thing ...
WEAVER : Whit Bissell is going to strike the creature
with a lantern in a minute , setting him afire .
How they did this was they got a stunt man named Al Wyatt , Rock Hudson 's stunt man ,
and they put him in a fire suit and they set him on fire .
Then they took that footage and they superimposed it over this shot here
of Ben Chapman , of the creature , waving his arms and pretending to be on fire .
But Bob Burns tells me that in 3D , the scene didn 't work .
He says that Wyatt must 've been closer to the 3D camera when he did his part
than Chapman was when Chapman did his scene .
Burns says that in 3-D , the creature and the fire
seem to be different distances away .
( GROANING )
WEAVER : Did you see that ? Did you notice the way
Antonio Moreno gave the impression
he was about to cover Whit Bissell with a sheet , like Bissell was dead ,
and then he put the sheet down again ?
I don 't know if they did that on purpose or not , but either way , it was a great fake-out .
Tough as Ricou Browning and Ben Chapman had it ,
the stunt man who played The Gill Man in the sequel ,
Revenge of the Creature , probably had it even tougher .
The Gill Man suits for Ricou and Ben were originally made in multiple pieces ,
and they had what are called flex gaps near the elbows , the shoulders and knees ,
which gave Ricou and Ben a little bit of freedom and mobility whenever they moved .
But The Gill Man suit worn by stunt man Tom Hennesy in Revenge of the Creature
was a molded one-piece bodysuit ,
which Bob Burns , who 's had to wear suits like that in his time ,
tells me are not made to flex ,
they give the guy inside no freedom , and they 're very uncomfortable .
There were two sequels to Creature from the Black Lagoon .
Revenge of the Creature , made in 1954 , and The Creature Walks Among Us , made in 1955 .
Ricou Browning played the underwater Gill Man in all three .
In Revenge , the above-water Gill Man was played by Tom Hennesy ,
and in Creature Walks , where the creature is seriously burned in a fire ,
the smooth-skinned Gill Man was played by actor Don Megowan .
The only name you 'll see listed in the credits for makeup is Bud Westmore ,
but he was just the head of the makeup department .
He did very little of the work .
He liked to make out he did , he was a self-promoter and a publicity hound ,
and for most every Universal international monster movie ,
there are a bunch of photos of Westmore painstakingly working on the thing ,
Westmore in his white shirt and tie and his sweater .
I mean , that was a tip-off right there . Nobody who 's really doing any work
in a makeup lab wears an outfit like that while he 's working .
But that 's how Westmore would show up when photos were going to be taken .
There 's a funny story I shouldn 't tell , but I will , about sculptor Chris Mueller ,
the very talented guy who sculpted The Gill Man 's head and hands .
He started out as an architectural sculptor , and his career went back aways .
He worked on Sabu , Thief of Bagdad , sculpting the temple and the all-seeing god .
He sculpted animals for The Jungle Book ,
and the giant squid for the Disney 20000 Leagues Under the Sea ,
and he also worked at Universal , doing architectural stuff at first ,
and then gravitating into the makeup department .
He sculpted the hunchback and the phantom for Man of a Thousand Faces ,
the Hyde mask for A and C Meet Jekyll and Hyde ,
the mummy for A and C Meet the Mummy , et cetera , et cetera .
Anyway , one day Mueller is there at Universal , working on The Gill Man head ,
and somebody else there tipped him off .
The guy told Mueller , " Look , if Bud Westmore comes in here
" and tells you to take the rest of the day off , don 't do it .
" What that means is that the press is gonna be coming in to take pictures ,
" and Westmore doesn 't want you around . "
Well , Mueller goes back to work and some time goes by ,
and sure enough , in comes Bud Westmore .
Westmore looks at the creature head Mueller 's sculpting and he says ,
" Oh , Chris , that 's just great . Man , you 're doin ' a terrific job .
" Hey , look , why don 't you take the rest of the day off ? "
And Mueller , still working on the creature head , tells Westmore , " No , I wanna finish . "
Again Westmore tells him , " Chris , look , you 're doing great work ,
" take some time off , take it easy . "
But Mueller doesn 't budge . " No , no , no . I don 't wanna go . I 'm almost finished .
" I 'm so close to being finished . I can finish this today . "
And what could Westmore say to that ?
Well , out Westmore goes and then half an hour , or an hour , or whatever later ,
sure enough , here comes Westmore back in again , this time with the press corps .
Westmore in his sporty little outfit , goes over to where Mueller is working ,
and he picks up one of Mueller 's sculpting tools
and he holds the thing right up to the creature head ,
but he doesn 't even touch the head with the tool
probably because he didn 't know what the hell he was doing .
Mueller 's standing behind the creature head , still working ,
and the photographer starts snapping away .
Anyway , the pictures are published and the captions say ,
" Bud Westmore at work on his newest creation , the creature . "
No mention of Mueller , but sure enough , there he was in the pictures .
Because of where Mueller was standing , they couldn 't crop him out .
Mueller got a kick out of that , and he used to enjoy telling that story .
- Lucas . Lucas , start your winch . - Eh ?
WEAVER : The Gill Man outfit was very expensive , needless to say .
According to Universal 's publicity department ,
which probably inflated some of these figures ,
it was valued at $ 18,000 ,
and was the product of eight-and-a-half months of research and experimentation .
" Fashioned of foam rubber , plastic ,
" hidden controls and specially-tailored fittings ,
" the costume forms the end result of 76 different body sketches ,
" 32 different head models ,
" and 176 pounds of foam rubber used during the experimental stages . "
There were articles about The Gill Man suit in different magazines ,
including non-movie magazines like Mechanix Illustrated .
There were also behind-the-scenes photos and an article in Skin Diver magazine .
According to Skin Diver , the August 1954 issue ,
Creature , which had only been out a couple of months at that point ,
had already grossed two million .
- Take it away ! - ( WINCH WHIRRING )
Take it up .
More , more .
WEAVER : Hey , the cracked boom has mysteriously fixed itself .
I mentioned earlier that The Gill Man outfit had flex gaps
that gave the people inside a little bit of freedom , but not a heck of a lot ,
and obviously , it was a lot of time and trouble
getting the actors in and out of the costume .
When it was time for lunch ,
Ben Chapman would take off the helmet , the boots and the gloves ,
and they had for him a stand-up chair .
It looked like a chaise lounge , except that it stood straight up and had armrests on it .
He 'd get into that , and there would be a very high table for him to eat off of .
Ben Chapman also played the creature on TV in 1954 .
He had a gag-cameo appearance in an episode of The Colgate Comedy Hour ,
with Abbott and Costello , and , playing the Frankenstein monster , Glenn Strange .
Universal , no doubt , considered TV a threat ,
the way most every other studio in Hollywood did ,
but they used it to promote the movie anyway .
They let Chapman go on The Colgate Comedy Hour .
And Julie Adams made some promotional appearances ,
and they even had a trailer for the movie running on TV ,
which caused a little bit of a squawk .
A couple of TV stations refused to run it ,
but at least one person at Universal took that as a compliment to the movie ,
and he wrote in a memo ,
" I can 't think of higher praise for what we have to sell on TV
" for Creature from the Black Lagoon ,
" than to have a station refuse a spot
" because it considered the material too scary .
" We have had two such incidents locally , one with KTTV , which is a DuMont affiliate ,
" and KNBH , the NBC station . In both instances , it related primarily
" to placement between programs with large juvenile followings .
" We finally won our point with KNBH , but it took considerable haranguing . "
Creature had the same producer , and director , and some of the same writers ,
as It Came from Outer Space , so it isn 't surprising that a few echoes
from that plot should turn up in this movie .
In It Came from Outer Space ,
Richard Carlson was an egghead and a peacenik
who wants the Xenomorphs left alone ,
and throughout the movie , he clashes with the hard-headed sheriff ,
and it culminated in a fistfight .
The relationship between Carlson and Richard Denning in Creature
develops pretty much the same way , and they too come to blows ,
at almost precisely the same spot in the picture .
The New York Times , in their original review of Creature , complained ,
" It 's a fishing expedition that is necessary
" only if a viewer has lost all of his comic books .
" The proceedings above and underwater were filmed in 3-D
" to impart an illusion of depth when viewed through polarized glasses .
" This adventure has no depth . "
Variety said , " The below-water scraps between skin-divers and the prehistoric thing
" are thrilling and will pop goose pimples on the susceptible fan ,
" as will the close-up scenes of the scaly , gilled creature .
" Jack Arnold 's direction has done a first-rate job of developing chills and suspense . "
The Hollywood Reporter : " Jack Arnold 's megging is briskly competent ,
" although too much time is wasted on underwater shots which are neither novel
" or dramatic enough to hold interest for the entire footage . "
We 're about to go underwater again .
This movie has about 18 minutes of underwater footage .
Everybody working underwater had scuba gear ,
but the way Ricou Browning worked underwater as The Gill Man was ,
he did what is called " hose-breathing . "
That 's something he knew how to do long before Creature .
Ricou says that his old boss ,
Newton Perry , the manager of Wakulla Springs ,
was probably one of the first people to ever breathe from an air hose underwater ,
and he taught Ricou and other people how to do it .
You 'd have an oxygen tank at the bottom of the spring
or , coming from the surface , just an air hose .
Ricou could stick the air hose in his mouth and breathe from it ,
like you would drink water from a hose in your back yard .
Ricou says they used to do hose-breathing
in the underwater shows at Weeki Wachee Springs .
That was how the mermaids in the show got their air .
Anyway , it was something Ricou could do very naturally .
He could just insert the hose in the mouth of the creature ,
then insert it a couple more inches to get it to his own mouth , and then breathe .
Ricou had several helpers and safety men
working with him at the bottom of Wakulla Springs ,
guys he 'd brought in himself . Some of them had worked with him in water shows ,
others had done some cave-diving with him .
As he was getting ready to do a scene , Ricou would just be down there underwater ,
ready to go , breathing from an air hose , with a safety man nearby .
When he was ready to go into a scene , he 'd give the cameraman a hand signal ,
but he would just stay in place , still breathing ,
waiting for the cameraman to signal him that the camera was rolling .
Ricou would then hand the hose to his safety man ,
swim into the scene and do what he had to do .
Let 's say it was just a swim-through , so he 'd swim right past the cameraman .
Then on the other side , there 'd be another safety man with another air hose .
Between the fact that he could hold his breath for a long period of time ,
and all the air hoses and safety men down there ,
he was able to stay underwater in the spring for long periods of time ,
even though he was the only person down there with no scuba gear .
If he got in trouble , if he ran out of air with no one nearby ,
what he 'd do was just stop whatever he was doing in the scene and go limp .
And that was his way of signaling his safety men
to swim over to him and give him an air hose .
Ricou tells a funny story about being out in the middle of the spring
and realizing he needed to go to the bathroom .
Somebody offered to take him ashore in a boat ,
but Ricou said , " No , don 't bother , " he 'd just swim ashore .
He swam underwater , because he said swimming underwater
was sometimes easier than swimming on the surface ,
and he got to a ladder that was on the dock next to shore .
He climbs up the ladder , still dressed as The Gill Man , needless to say ,
and all of a sudden , right there in front of him ,
was some lady and her little girl .
And the little girl started screaming .
Rico said , " She started screaming and running .
" And the mother went after her , and I went after both of them ,
" trying to say , ' Hey , hey , it 's okay . It 's okay . ' But me saying ' it 's okay ' didn 't do a thing .
" They took off and that 's the last I saw of them .
" But I never went out of my way to try and scare anybody , no .
" From then on , I made sure I kept the head off whenever I came ashore . "
Ben Chapman , on the other hand , liked to occasionally scare people .
He says that a lot of folks used to come and visit the sets and watch them shoot ,
including guests of people who worked at Universal .
And what Ben would do when he knew people were coming was
he 'd swim out to the middle of Park Lake
and just float there , with just the top of a helmet and the eyes showing .
He 'd stay like that and watch until he saw the people arrive ,
and then he 'd swim under the water
and come bursting up through the water like a porpoise ,
and then go under again . He 'd make it hard for them to really see him .
" Then I would swim in towards them
" with just the eyes and the top of the head showing .
" I 'd swim in this way , getting as close to the shore as I could .
" Of course , it 's becoming shallower and shallower .
" I 'd swim in to where it was about a foot-and-a-half deep ,
" and then all of a sudden , I would stand right up and ... "
Ben let out a roar .
Ben said some of the guests would just about wet their pants .
Audiences loved the underwater scenes .
Bob Burns saw Creature in 3D when it was new ,
and he says that in the underwater scenes , the water seemed to disappear ,
and it looked like The Gill Man was just floating in midair
in front of the screen in the theater . He said it was just amazing .
There was a preview of Creature
at the United Artists Theatre in Los Angeles on January 7 , 1954 ,
and on the cards the people were asked to fill out , one of the questions was ,
" Which scene did you like most ? "
Well , the underwater scenes were the hands-down winner .
Funnily enough , talk about a sign of changing times ,
in answer to the question , " Which scenes , if any , did you dislike ? "
More than one person complained about Kay 's line ,
" David and I are together all the time anyway . "
To them , that meant that they were living together without being married ,
and they squawked about that .
One person said he disliked all of it , especially
" when Kay made like Esther Williams , not the time or place for it . "
Some of the other comments :
" Most exciting picture I have ever witnessed . "
" Give us more pictures like this , only in color . "
" I 'm a bundle of nerves . I 'll never go swimming in a lagoon . "
" The spookiest picture I have ever seen , and screamed throughout . "
One person complained the plot
was a little too much like The Thing ,
and believe it or not , there is some truth in that .
But nobody mentioned King Kong , which was the inspiration .
As I mentioned before ,
watch Creature and Revenge back-to-back next time , and you can 't miss it .
As a matter of fact , one early script of Revenge of the Creature
ended with The Gill Man being shot , not by the sheriff 's posse ,
but by a guy , or guys , shooting at him from a helicopter ,
just like the biplane pilots who killed King Kong .
Maybe we won 't have to fight him on his own terms after all .
WEAVER : Speaking of the preview , or one of the previews anyway ,
Arthur Ross , who co-wrote the picture , told me an interesting anecdote about it .
A fellow named Ed Muhl was the head of production at Universal ,
and according to Ross ,
" He sensed something in Creature that nobody else did
" and they sort of laughed at him ,
" but he said it was going to be an absolute smash .
" For the preview of Creature , there were three buses filled with people .
" They took us to dinner at the Beachcomber , and then downtown for the preview .
" Ed made every executive , every contract producer ,
" every contract director come watch Creature , because , he said ,
" ' This is going to be the pattern and form and intent of our future films . '
" At that point , Harry Essex and I looked at each other and said , ' He must be crazy ! " '
Well , Ed Muhl turned out not to be crazy . Creature cost Universal $ 463,700 ,
and by the end of 1954 , it had already grossed three million .
Another negative review of Creature came from the Los Angeles Daily News .
" As the action unreels with the speed of an anchor being hoisted ,
" Miss Adams changes bathing suits several times ,
" walks woodenly and persistently into danger ,
" and screams so often and so loud that little babes in the audience grew pale . "
Julie Adams , who shot this scene on her 27th birthday , has just screamed again .
If I was with Bissell , I 'd be more worried
about Richard Carlson swinging that bat around
than I 'd be about the creature .
When Bissell 's young daughters saw Creature in a theater ,
this scene came on , and one of ' em stood up in the middle of the theater
and screamed , " It 's going after Daddy ! "
He 'll be back .
WEAVER : I mentioned before that Milicent Patrick
was one of the designers of The Gill Man
and actually worked on the suit itself , and then , because she was a looker ,
Universal sent her out on a tour to drum up interest in the movie .
Universal was going to promote Patrick as " the beauty who created the beast , "
but Bud Westmore , protecting his turf , took exception to that .
Westmore claimed that the creation of the creature was completely his own work .
Westmore , lying through his teeth ,
said that many people had been involved in the original sketches and thinking ,
but had all dropped out of the project when it became difficult and complex .
As a result , he said , he spent four or five weeks himself
developing the model which was eventually used .
So , at a staff meeting , they talked about this and they decided to call Milicent Patrick
" the beauty who lives with the beasts , " instead .
But even that didn 't satisfy Westmore .
A couple days later , he barged into the office of an executive named Sam Israel
and said that he resented the whole project .
Sam Israel wrote in a memo , " He is perturbed by the fact that Milicent
" will claim credit for what he has achieved in putting these monsters together ,
" and he would like us to make sure that , as far as possible ,
" the interviews stress the fact that he is the one who supervises
" the creation of these creatures from start to finish .
" Milicent 's job , he says , is merely to put his ideas in the form of sketches .
" Frankly , I am getting a little fed up
" with these squawks from people who are paid to do a job .
" And from what I hear , Milicent 's contribution in this work is very important . "
Well , Milicent Patrick went on a whirlwind tour .
She did a jillion print interviews , and she appeared on radio and TV .
She was on the Today Show with Dave Garroway
and she made personal appearances at theaters that were showing Creature ,
and busybody Bud Westmore made it his business
to get hold of newspapers from a number of the cities she had visited .
He discovered that she was being credited as the designer of the creature ,
and he made it known that he wasn 't going to use her as a sketch artist anymore .
Some of the suits at Universal tried to make Westmore understand
that she herself did everything possible to credit him ,
and if there was any blame in the matter ,
it was Universal 's fault or the newspapers ' fault .
One of the executives , who was exchanging memos with another executive
about this situation , wrote ,
" It would be most unfair if Westmore were to discontinue
" using the services of Patrick as a result of his pique .
" The facts are that we haven 't had a more cooperative person on tour
" than Miss Patrick . And in every interview ,
" she made it clear that she worked for Bud Westmore .
" And she plugged Westmore as head of makeup ,
" and followed the instructions that we gave to her .
" Patrick conducted herself beyond any criticism from any point of view . "
I 've got a copy of Millicent Patrick 's résumé , and unfortunately ,
it doesn 't look like she ever worked as a sketch artist at Universal again .
This is supposed to be a very dramatic moment .
Julie Adams is so glad Richard Carlson is safe ,
but it 's so obvious she doesn 't wanna get wet ,
I 'm sure because that lake water was probably cold .
And it was definitely cold at night .
Richard Denning remembers shooting out in the lake one cold October night .
They were out in the water and they were tired , and it was late ,
and a prop man kept bringing them brandy to keep them from freezing to death .
" It worked great , and we were going just fine ,
" and then we finally wrap it up and we go to the dressing rooms .
" They 're nice and warm , and all of a sudden ... "
And Denning starts slurring his words here .
" ... that brandy just hit us like a sledgehammer .
" But out in the cold and the wet and wind , it didn 't bother us at all . "
Ricou Browning had the same thing happen thousands of miles away .
He says everybody was trying to be nice , and they kept bringing him brandy ,
and pretty soon , they were working with a drunken creature .
So Ricou figured he 'd better cut that out .
DAVID : She 's coming . Back .
WEAVER : I think the idea of a drunken creature is kind of cute .
Julie Adams has kind of a soft spot for the creature in her heart , I guess .
She told me , " The creature scared people , but there was also a sweetness about it .
" In the real classics ,
" there always is that feeling of compassion for the monster .
" I think maybe it touches something in ourselves ,
" maybe the darker parts of ourselves
" that long to be loved and think they really can 't ever be loved .
" It strikes a chord within us .
" That 's what Creature from the Black Lagoon did . "
DAVID : Stand by to pull her up with the winch .
Pull her in .
( WINCH WHIRRING )
DAVID : That 's it .
Whoa !
I 'll go down and unfasten it .
- Give me slack ! - ( GROWLING )
WEAVER : We 're about to get a good look at
the creature 's gills pulsating as he breathes .
How they did that was , rubber tubes came into the back of Ben Chapman 's helmet ,
through the dorsal fin , and ran into the gills ,
where there were little balloons or air pockets .
On the other end of the hose ,
there was a guy sitting off camera with a little hand pump .
Chapman and this other fellow coordinated and worked together to create the effect .
Chapman would open his mouth and gasp
at the same time that the hand-pump guy would pump the gills .
That way , it looked like the gasping was what made the gills flare out .
Julie Adams is replaced in this shot by stuntwoman Polly Burson ,
who got swept off the boat by Ben Chapman .
No , don 't shoot , don 't shoot ! You might hit Kay .
WEAVER : And now we cut to a scene shot in Florida ,
Ricou Browning swimming underwater with Ginger Stanley in his arms .
That was our next-to-last shot at Ricou .
From now on , it 'll be Ben Chapman right up until the last shot of the movie .
Ricou Browning was recently profiled in People magazine
in connection with Creature .
But he says he 's more proud of a lot of the other things he 's done .
He writes , he 's directed , he created the TV series Flipper ,
he directed the underwater parts of Thunderball , and to him ,
Creature was just another movie , just another job .
Ben Chapman , on the other hand , revels in having played The Gill Man ,
and he regularly appears at sci-fi cons and autograph shows .
He 's also given a lot of thought to what made The Gill Man so popular .
Here 's a little bit of music from The Wolf Man as Richard Carlson climbs out of the water .
Chapman says that if you look back at all the thrillers that Universal made ,
The Phantom , The Hunchback , Frankenstein , Dracula , The Mummy , and Creature ,
" they were all very successful . And why ?
" If you 'll think about it , they were all Beauty and the Beast .
" The phantom was in love with the girl , the hunchback loved his Esmeralda ,
" the Mummy had his princess . They would never hurt the girl ,
" only the people that got in their way .
" And The Gill Man was the same type of monster character .
" After that , of course , movies changed , Universal changed ,
" stories changed , people 's attitudes changed ,
" and now the studios are not coming out with the quality thrillers they made before .
" Now it 's all blood and gore . But in the old days , these Universal pictures
" were all well done , and the best of ' em were all Beauty and the Beast .
" And my pride is that I was the original creature from the Black Lagoon . "
As I mentioned before , these cave scenes were shot on the process stage at Universal .
The cave walls were made of plaster , but they were still hard as a rock .
In the scene where Ben Chapman carried Julie Adams through there ,
he was wearing the medium-sized eyes , and he couldn 't see very well ,
and the cave was dark and narrow to begin with .
Well , he banged her head against the rock wall .
She let out a yelp , and she was hurt .
Not badly , but she had a cut or a bruise on her forehead ,
so a nurse had to come in and look at it .
There 's a classic shot of Adams
having a bandage put on her forehead by the nurse on the grotto set ,
and gathered around her are Jack Arnold , Richard Denning , Richard Carlson ,
and , squatting down and looking very concerned , the creature .
I like this bit here of Carlson getting lifted in the air .
And another nice touch is that when the creature puts him down ,
notice the claw marks on Carlson .
He 's got puncture wounds from the creature 's thumbs
on the sides of his stomach
and if you look closely ,
he 's got gashes from the creature 's other eight fingers
on the sides of his back .
DAVID : No , no more . Let him go .
WEAVER : In the Maurice Zimm treatment , Black Lagoon ,
The Gill Man is shot up and then devoured by piranha .
A later draft of the script ended with Reed killing The Gill Man on the deck of the boat
with an ax , " the ax protruding from the neck of The Gill Man ,
" apparently embedded there , cutting the spinal cord .
" As The Gill Man falls , the ax is pulled from Reed 's grasp .
" Camera slowly pulls back to a full shot . No one moves or speaks . "
Well , a conclusive ending like that wouldn 't do .
Jack Arnold told an interviewer that the reason
The Gill Man wasn 't destroyed more decisively was ,
" The studio wanted to keep him in there for a sequel , and I also loved him .
" I used to call him The Beastie and I wanted to leave it a little open ,
" not show him destroyed . I thought he was very sympathetic ,
" due in no small way to the work of Ricou Browning . "
Well , Arnold was right about Ricou Browning ,
and he was right about Universal thinking , " Sequel . "
Even before Creature was released ,
the outline for Revenge of the Creature was written .
The studio had no intention of letting what was , at that time ,
the best articulated full-body monster costume ever made ,
go to waste after just one movie .
Weeks after Creature went into release , an outline temporarily titled
Sequel to Creature from the Black Lagoon was already on William Alland 's desk ,
dated February 26th , 1954 ,
and opening with the lines ,
" The Rita chugs slowly up the Amazon .
" They are on their way to the Black Lagoon to see if The Gill Man is still alive . "
I 'm Tom Weaver . Thank you for listening .